<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sober advice to church-wardens in a letter to  a church-warden in London, from his friend out o7the countrey, and may serve indifferently for constables, and others, who are required to make presentments for not going to their parish-churches, or communicating, &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60706</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4400</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41687</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">31355770</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 31355770</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110664</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60706)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110664)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1753:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sober advice to church-wardens in a letter to  a church-warden in London, from his friend out o7the countrey, and may serve indifferently for constables, and others, who are required to make presentments for not going to their parish-churches, or communicating, &amp;c.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for F. Smith, Senior ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government.</term>
               <term>Church attendance.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110664:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SOBER ADVICE TO CHURCH-WARDENS, IN A LETTER TO A CHURCH-WARDEN <hi>IN LONDON,</hi> From his Friend out of the Countrey, And may ſerve indifferently for Conſtables, and others, who are required to make Preſentments for not go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Pariſh-Churches, &amp; Communicating, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Id Tantum poſſumus quod Jure poſſumus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>F. Smith</hi> Senior, at the <hi>Elephant</hi> and <hi>Caſtle,</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:110664:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:110664:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Kind Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Received yours, and am heartily ſorry to hear of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity uſed and intended againſt Proteſtant Diſſenters, for their Nonconformity; becauſe I am throughly perſwaded many of them are ſincere and harmleſs in their Diſſent, and give as good Teſtimony of their being ſo, as we generally do of our ſincerity in our Diſſent from Popery; however cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to Penalties without Infringment of our Proteſtant Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples: But ſince ſome of our Eccleſiaſtical Rulers and Judges are not of this mind, but requires by publick charge that all Perſons Aged above Sixteen Years, ſhould take the Sacrament now at <hi>Eaſter,</hi> or to be preſented by the Churchwardens or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the place, to be proceeded againſt by Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with all its grievous Concomitants and Conſequents, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of perpetual Impriſonment is now in the leaſt. You deſire my advice; What you, being ſworn Church-warden, ſhould do in this caſe? You are very loath to have ſo great a hand in the Ruin of your honeſt Neighbours for their Conſcience towards God, and on the other ſide you muſt be true to that Duty, which you have obliged your ſelf before God to perform. You know (my Friend) I am not one of the Learned in the Common nor Civil Laws, and therefore can only tell you what courſe my ſelf a private Perſon, willing to keep a good Conſcience towards God and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Men, would do in ſuch a caſe. And you are pleaſed to tell me, you therefore deſire my adviſe, becauſe that I being of like condition, and in like circumſtances with your ſelf, am more likely to give advice fit for you than they whoſe education has enured their minds to Subtilties and Quirks of Law. I can eaſily grant the Reaſon you give of your Choice to be good, but I cannot allow your application of it to me; for though I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved in the power of God to be honeſt, yet there is another quality wanting to make me a fit adviſer in ſo nice a caſe, to wit, an underſtanding well exerciſed in diſcerning between good and evil, and things indifferent: But I may remember, you only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to know my opinion, you do not oblige your ſelf to follow it,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110664:3"/>neither would I have you to do ſo, without better Judgments then I can pretend to, except you find my Reaſons to be convincing.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place I am ſorry you have taken the Church-wardens Oath, which obliges you; <hi>to Execute the Office of a Church-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in your Pariſh for the enſuing Year, according to his Majeſties Laws Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> for its a difficulty ſcarcely to be overcome by the moſt Skilful, to reſolve what Eccleſiaſtical Laws are in force, what not, therefore beyond your capacity to execute according to what you know not, and give me leave to mind you by the way, that Reaſon, Equity, and Religion requires, that we ſhould never proceed to imputation of Crimes or Executions of Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in doubtful Caſes. In matters of favour and benefit we may be liberal, but in matters of hurt and damage to our Neighbour, we ſhould be ſo far from any thing of that nature in a contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted point, that we ſhould not go to the utmoſt the Law al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, though in a moſt clear Caſe. Now if the Statute of 1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. chap. 2. be revived by Repeal of that Statute which Repealed it, the Eceleſiaſtical Perſons ought to uſe the Kings Name and Seal to their Proceſſes, and their holding Courts in their own Names is contrary to Law. However, it is at leaſt doubtful, whether they have any legal Power, and likewiſe whether any of their Cannons have any force of Law; If then you make pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments to thoſe Courts, whereby your Neighbour is vexed and indamaged, you know not but you may therein be injurous to your Neighbour without legal Authority, which no wife and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious Man will venture.</p>
            <p>But, Secondly. I conceive that a Man choſen Church-warden, may lawfully refuſe that Oath, as being contrary to Law, as may appear by a Statute made in the Thirteenth of this King, chap. 2. and incited in the prohibition for <hi>Waterfield,</hi> where it is enacted <hi>that it ſhall not be lawful for any Arch-Biſhop, Biſhop, Vicar, Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Chancellour, Commiſſary, or any other Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Judge, Officer, or Miniſter, or any other Perſon having or exerciſing Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, to Tender, Offer, or Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to any Perſon whatſoever, the Oath uſually called the Oath</hi> ex Officio, <hi>or any other Oath whereby ſuch Perſons to whom the ſame is Tendered or Adminiſtred, may be charged or compelled to confeſs, or accuſe, or purge him or her ſelf of any criminal matter or thing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he or ſhe may be liable to Conſures or Puniſhments.</hi> But I am
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110664:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>perſwaded that no Man that makes Conſcience of an Oath, but will find himſelf obliged by the Laws Eccleſiaſtical (ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing all thoſe to be in force which the Official ſays are in force) burdened and compelled to confeſs, or accuſe himſelf of ſome criminal matter or thing, and therefore ſuch Oath ought not to be Adminiſtred to him. However, having taken that Oath, you muſt endeavour to perform it as well as you can without breach of the Laws of God, or Laws of the Land, which latter muſt always give place to the former, and by them be made new or interpreted.</p>
            <p>In the next place as to the buſineſs of preſenting thoſe of above Sixteen Years of Age, that come not to the Sacrament at <hi>Eaſter.</hi> Firſt, I ſay it is contrary to Chriſtianity and all civility of Neighbourhood, to preſent a Man as a Criminal, ſo to expoſe him to ſo dreadful a Sentence as Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and all Calamities that attend it, without firſt diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their Neighbour to know what he can ſay for himſelf in Vindication, for in this Caſe the preſentment of one or two Church-wardens, is of as much force, and more dangerous conſequence than the preſentment of Twelve or more of the moſt ſubſtantial Men of the County, in civil Caſes, and therefore the leaſt that the Church-warden can do, is to hear what his Neighbour can ſay for himſelf, before he put him into ſo much trouble and danger, as ſuch an accuſation amounts to. For there may be divers lawful and reaſonable Excuſes of a Mans not coming to Church ſuch a Month, or not coming to the Communion at <hi>Eaſter;</hi> as for inſtance, ſuppoſe a Man be Sick and not able to come, or have had buſineſs abroad for One, Two, or Three Months together at the time of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> are not theſe and ſuch like lawful Excuſes? I remember the Statute of <hi>Eliz.</hi> 23. chap. 1. (to retain the Queens Majeſties Subjects in their due obedience) made againſt Papiſts, (but now put in uſe againſt Proteſtants) ſays, <hi>That every Perſon above the Age of Sixteen Years, which ſhall not repair to ſome Church or Chappel, or uſual place of Common-Prayer, but forbearing the ſame contrary to the Tenor of a Statute made in the Firſt Year of Her Majeſties Reign, for Uniformity of Common-Prayer,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhall forfeit,</hi> &amp;c. now that Statute re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to, has this exception in it, (viz.) <hi>Having no lawful or
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110664:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>reaſonable excuſe to be abſent,</hi> which plainly ſhews there may be lawful or reaſonable excuſe of being abſent from Church for a Week or Month, and conſequently of not taking the Sacrament Adminiſtred at that time, therefore I conclude the Church-warden or other Officers, who preſent any of his Neighbours as guilty of ſuch a Crime before he have heard what he can ſay for himſelf, is Unjuſt, Unchriſtian, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neighbourly; Unjuſt, becauſe the light of Nature will not permit it that any ſhould be condemned unheard; Unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, becauſe the Law of Chriſt commands us not to Judge leaſt we be Judged, and conſequently Unneighbourly, becauſe ſomewhat more of civility ought to be ſhewed to Chriſtians that are of the ſame Vicinage, then to Men as Men, or to Chriſtians barely as Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Perhaps you will ſay, it is ſufficient for you to ground an Information or Preſentment upon, that in Fact a Man did not come to his Pariſh Church, or did not take the Sacrament there at <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and that if he have any lawful or reaſonable excuſe, he muſt urge it upon his Trial before the Judge or Commiſſary. But Sir, would you be ſo dealt with? Be charged with a Crime that has heavy Penalties attending to it? Be put to the trouble and expence in Defending your ſelf in a Court where ſome Men love none more than their own Souls? When if their Officer would but take the pains to ſpeak with you, you would eaſily Vindicate your ſelf from that charge? Beſides, it is to be conſidered that all Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Grand Juries, and others, are choſen out of the Neighbourhood, as being therefore ſuppoſed to know what may be known of the Innocency or Guiltineſs of a Perſon they Accuſe or Condemn, and they are Twelve at leaſt, ſometimes Twenty One of a Grand Inqueſt, that if ſome be Ignorant, others may be knowing in the Matter and Perſon brought before them, and they muſt be honeſt and free, and legal Men, ſuch as the Law in every circumſtance requires, <hi>if there be but One in Twelve,</hi> otherwiſe their proceedings will be null and void.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:110664:4"/>
But Sir, Your Preſentment, as I have ſaid, hath the validity of the Preſentment of a full Grand In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt upon Oath; Nay more, (except when the Cauſe of Recuſances come before a Grand Inqueſt) for upon your Preſentment the Biſhop or his Official concludes your Neighbour Guilty, and will perhaps not admit of his lawful excuſes, not as in other Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, bring Witneſſes face to face to prove him Guilty; for you have already convicted him by your Preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; again, in numerous Pariſhes, ſuch as you have about <hi>London,</hi> it is impoſſible for you to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther every one did Communicate, and therefore you can only ſay, that ſo far as you know ſuch a Man or ſuch a Woman did not Communicate, and that ſhall create your Neighbour no ſmall vexation, though at length he proves that he did Communicate in his own Pariſh, or in ſome other Church or allowed Chappel, and that you are miſtaken in your ſworn Preſentments.</p>
            <p>But you will now ask me, is it my place to Judge what are lawful or reaſonable excuſes, muſt not I leave that to the Eccleſiaſtical Court, whoſe Duty it is to determine ſuch matters.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, I have already ſhewed you that in your Preſentment, you are preſently both Accuſer, Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Jury; So that the Proceedings in that Court are of the Nature of a Plea, after Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, as is in another Court brought againſt the Sentence ready to be paſſed, for as in a Civil Court the Party found Guilty, is asked what he has to ſay, why Judgment of Execution ſhould not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110664:5"/>paſs upon him? So here the Spiritual Iudge does but in effect asle a Man what he has to ſay, why the Penalties of ſuch a Crime ſhould not be Executed upon him? And ſince you are in a real Sence a Judge, all the Reaſon of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind will oblige you not only to hear, but to determine concerning the circumſtances of the Action you are to Judge.</p>
            <p>Is it reaſonable or conſiſtant with the Liborties of Engliſh Men, that a Man ſhould be liable to ſuffer ſo great Vexation and Dammage, as the Preſentment of the Church-warden puts him to, and the Church-warden not at liberty to Judge of his reaſonable Defence againſt that Vexation? When in a Civil Court for a Crime or Treſpaſs, to the value of a Groat, a Man ſhall have Firſt Twelve at leaſt of his Sworn Neighbours to paſs Judgment upon him; every one of which muſt be ſatisfied the Accuſed Party has no reaſonable excuſe, that is, every one muſt be ſatisfied that there is ſufficient Evidence of his Guilt by their own Knowledge, or credible Witneſſes, or Oath, and after that the Accuſed Party and the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes muſt be heard together, to the ſatisfaction of Twelve Jurors more, who muſt every one agree to the Condemnation or elſe he ſhall be cleared, but in the Spiritual way of preceending the buſineſs of the Firſt Twelve or Grand Jury, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps of Twenty Three, and of Witneſſes, is all done by the Church-warden, that's moſt manifeſt, and the Verdict of the other Twelve, or Pettit Jury is alſo given by the Church-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110664:5"/>and the Spiritual Judge has no more to do but to paſs Sentence, as the Civil Judg doth when the Verdict is brought in.<note n="*" place="margin">For his admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Men thrice in a Breath, is in it ſelf a Penal Sentence, being but a Prologue to Excommunication and Impriſonment, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when things impoſſible are required; but that's impoſſible, which a man cannot do without Sin.</note> The vaſt difference between thoſe two ways of Proceeding, ſhews, that the one is of <hi>Rome,</hi> the other of <hi>England.</hi> But muſt the Church-warden do the Work of two Juries toward the Ruine of a Man and his Family, and not judge of a man's rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Defence againſt his Sentence?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If the Church-warden muſt not judge of lawful or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Excuſes, but muſt preſent Men, merely becauſe of Omiſſion to take the Sacrament at <hi>Eaſter,</hi> then how comes it to paſs they can diſpence with their Obligation of preſenting thoſe that notoriouſly offend in other matters, and even themſelves for the moſt part, if not all of them, to which Preſentment they are equally obliged? For by the 109. Canon, ſuppoſing them in Force (which is a great Queſtion, or rather out of Queſtion, not being confirmed by any Act of Parliament) they are obliged to preſent <hi>thoſe that offend their Brethren by manifeſt Drunkenneſs, Swearing, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, or any other Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitude or Wickedneſs.</hi> By the Statute of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> ch. 2. <hi>All perſons are obliged to endeavour themſelves to reſort to their Pariſh Church, or ſome other place, having no lawful or reaſonable Excuſe to be abſent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every</hi> Sunday <hi>and Holyday.</hi> Now I perſwade my ſelf, that in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, there are but few People, or Church wardens themſelves that are not guilty of the Breach of this Statute moſt Holydays in the Year: And the Church-wardens know it perfectly: How is it then that they do not preſent them, except that they either know or preſume they have ſome lawful or reaſonable Excuſe to be abſent, and if they take upon them to judge of reaſonable Excuſes in this Caſe, ſo as to excuſe, themſelves from the Breach of their Oath, why not in other Caſes alſo, and particularly in the caſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion at <hi>Eaſter,</hi> wherein they certainly know there may be the like Excuſes? And the ſame Argument will hold in the caſe of thoſe that come not to Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in a Month, contrary to the Tenour of this Statute, who are puniſhable by the Forfeiture of 20 <abbr>
                  <hi>l.</hi>
               </abbr> a Month, by the Statute of 23 of <hi>Eliz.</hi> ch. 1. made againſt Papiſts.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:110664:6"/>
Fourthly, This Statute of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> makes it not abſolutely crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, <hi>Not to reſort to their Pariſh, or ſome other Church, but not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour themſelves to reſort,</hi> &amp;c. Now a man may endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> tho' he do not perform, being hindered by ſome lawful or reaſonable Lett;<note n="*" place="margin">Nay, I am well aſſured, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny who reſort not to their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> do endeavour themſelves to reſort, more by far than thoſe that do: They read, confer; ſtudy and pray more for Satisfaction in the Lawfulneſs of it.</note> ſo that a Church-warden that preſents a Man for not coming to his Pariſh Church for a Holyday or a Month, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting with him whether he had any reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Excuſe of being abſent, or whether he was not at ſome other Church or Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; and without judging of reaſonable Letts, is injurious to his Neighbour beyond the Statute; and if he may not judge of lawful and reaſonable Excuſes; but muſt preſent a man notwithſtanding, he makes a falſe. Preſentment, becauſe he does not know whether it be true or no that a man did not endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to reſort to Church, It may be falſe; and if it be true, it's more than he knows, tho' upon Oath he pretends to know it; ſo commits Perjury: He ſwears neither in Truth nor Judgment, nor Righteouſneſs, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4, 2. And why may not a lawful or reaſonable Lett come in a Mans way at Eaſter, as well as at another time? Which if it were ſo, the Church-warden ought not to conclude him guilty of a wilful omiſſion and therefore ought not to preſent him.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, In crimes there is the matter or fact, and the manner or Circumſtances of that fact, the matter or fact is for the moſt part neither good nor evil, but according to Circumſtances which make it the one or the other. So under the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> God comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to reſt on the Sabbath day, but if a man had fallen into a Ditch on the Sabbath it was evil to reſt, and not Labour to lift him out, for it was lawful to do ſo for an Ox or a Sheep, ſo in our Law, one may kill a Man, and be Innocent when he does it in his own Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary defence; but if in malice he is guilty of Murder: So to take a Mans Sword from him on the High-way is robbery, if it be done with a Fellonious intent; but to keep a Man from doing himſelf and others a miſchief it is good and lawful: In like manner, he that will preſent a Man to a Court to be puniſht as a prophane Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender, (as the Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> ſpeaks in his Order) for not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Church and receiving the Sacrament at Eaſter, ought firſt to be aſſur'd that he did it with a prophane Mind, and had no law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful or reaſonable Lett to excuſe him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:110664:6"/>
Having now, my Friend, ſhewed you that your Preſentment has the force of a Verdict, and the refore you ought to hear what your Neighbour has to ſay for himſelf before you bring in the Verdict of your Preſentment to the ſpiritual Judg for him to paſs Sentence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him: Having alſo clearly proved (as I ſuppoſe) that you are to judge of lawful and reaſonable Excuſes, and that you do it moſt frequently in other caſes: It remains now that I ſay ſomething of lawful and reaſonable Excuſes: The firſt Rule I ſhall lay down to diſcern them by ſhall be general, even that general Rule of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>Whatſoever ye would that men ſhould do unto you, do ye even ſo unto them.</hi> If your Neighbour give as good Teſtimony of his Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity in the Chriſtian Religion as you your ſelf, or at leaſt no Cauſe to the contrary, that which you would have to be judged a reaſonable excuſe in your own caſe, that ought you to think in his caſe. I deſcribe your Neighbour here to be in Appearance an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and true man, becauſe you are to believe what he ſays in his own Defence; which if he were a man of ill Fame, you could not reaſonably do; but if a man be of as good Credit as your ſelf, or you hear nothing againſt him, I ſee not how you can avoid giving the ſame credit to him you would have another give to your ſelf. (This is to be underſtood of ſuch cauſes, as, admit not of outward Evidence beſides a man's own Teſtimony) How otherwiſe do you love your Neighbour as your ſelf? which the Ap. <hi>James</hi> ſays is the <hi>Royal Law according to the Scriptures;</hi> and Chriſtian Charity is that which <hi>believeth all things, hopeth all things;</hi> to wit, which he hath no good Grounds to disbelieve and doubt.</p>
            <p>I proſume then that you and every Church-warden will judge, that Sickneſs of the Party, or any Relation, whom he or ſhe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in duty Wave without great danger, or alſo journeying in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reinparts about a Mans neceſſary Occaſions, or in our own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey about ſudden buſineſs that will not admit of delay, are reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble excuſes for not preſenting ones ſelf and communicating at his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh-Church at Eaſter; and there may be many other excuſes of the ſame Nature, which I will not Trouble you to enumerate: But from hence I aſſume, If the manifeſt danger of ones Health, or the very probable damage of a Mans worldly Eſtate, Credit or Liberty, be reaſonable excuſes to be admitted by the Church-warden; how much more reaſonable and to be allowed is that excuſe of ſinning againſt God by doing that which he cannot do in Faith or with a perſwaſion of its lawfulneſs when divine Authority ſays, <hi>Whatſoever
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110664:7"/>is not of Faith is Sin?</hi> For it were better for a Man to loſe all his Eſtate, his Credit, his Liberty, yea and his Life too then ſin againſt God. But he that judgeth any thing required of him to be ſinful and doth it, he certainly ſins: For he that in the Apoſtles time eat of thoſe meats, which were lawful to be eaten, judging them to be forbidden, or even doubting whether they were lawful, that Man was guilty of ſin and liable to be damn'd for the ſame. <hi>He that doubteth is damened if be eat, becauſe: he eateth not of Faith,</hi> Saith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 14.23. I will grant that it may ſo fall out that a Man may be ſo minded that he ſins both ways, whether he do that which is required or forbear it; but that is, when he his abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely oblig'd by God to do it, and he through an Ignorant or ill inform'd conſcience thinks it unlawful; but in the caſe we diſcourſe of, our Biſhops and Miniſters acknowledge that in the things doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of, by thoſe that do not frequent their Pariſh Churches there is no obſcure comand of God why they ſhould be done, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Duty (ſay they) by Humane Authority, which may be with-drawn, and being with-drawn they are no longer any Mans Duty, now how it comes to be in the power of Chriſtians, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer upon their Fullow Chriſtians, to do thoſe things which no Law of God or Chriſt oblige them to, and which their Fellow-Chriſtians account unlawful or doubt of; and to puniſh them for Diſobedience, when their Obediance would be a ſin againſt God, I leave you to determin. But if neither you, nor your Miniſter, nor yet your Biſhop can remove the doubts of theſe Ghriſtians, and if they behave themſelves as Chriſtians in Obedience to all things that Chriſt requireth of them, in Profeſſion of Chriſtian Faith, in Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Worſhip and Prayer, in the Celebration of the Lords Supper as they underſtand Chriſt to have commanded it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If you will not admit theſe People to be reaſonably excus'd of their abſence from their Pariſh Church, I doubt Chriſt will not exchſe you of injuſtice and uncharitableneſs at the great day: I confeſs the Proſecution of theſe People with penalties is not ſo great a Sin as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> cauſed Chriſtians to commit when his Name was <hi>Saul,</hi> before his Converſion; for he compell'd them to Blaſpheme; and ſinning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ones own conſcience in a matter of Circumſtance is not ſo bad as blaſpheming of Chriſt againſt ones Conſcience, but the ſame Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſays in a leſs caſe, <hi>When ye ſin ſo againſt the Brethren and wound their weak Conſeiences ye Sin againſt Chriſt.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8, 12. now that which you Brother cannot do without Sin, and that which you
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110664:7"/>cannot proſecute him for not doing without Sin, ſhould (me thinks) be a reaſonible excuſe both for him and you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> You will perhaps urge againſt what I have ſaid, that there is no other way, but this of preſenting them for not coming to Church, to convict Papiſts of Recuſancy; and that they alſo as well as Proteſtants may eſcape upon the pretence of Conſcience, ſo the Laws in theſe caſes provided, be made of no effect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To which I anſwer, that the caſe of Proteſtant Diſſenters and of Papiſts is not the ſame, but far different: For the reaſon why Papiſts do not communicate with Proteſtants in Pariſh Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches is, Their acknowledgment of a foreign Power and Authority Superior to that of the King and the Laws of the Land, namely, the Authority of the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> who is the declared Enemy of the King, and the People being Proteſtants whence it is that their not coming to Church is an effect and indication of that acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and againſt them were the Statutes of the 1ſt. and 23d. of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> made, the laſt whereof is: <hi>An Act to retain the Queen Majeſties Subjects in their due Obedience,</hi> and the Preſace gives this as the reaſon of making that Act, <hi>viz. That diverſe all diſpoſed Perſons have practiſed, by other means than by Bulls to withdraw diverſe the Queens Majeſties Subjects from their natural Obedience to her Majeſty, to obey the uſurped Authority of <hi>Rome</hi> and in reſpect of the ſame, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade great numbers to withdraw their due Obedience to her Majeſties Laws eſtabliſhed for the due Service of Almighty God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For it is obſerved by the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> in his charge at <hi>Norwich,</hi> and by others, that not any Papiſts, during the firſt ten years of that Queens Reign, did refuſe to come to Church; that <hi>Cornwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, Beddingfield</hi> and <hi>Eylyard,</hi> were the firſt Recuſants in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the eleventh year of her Majeſties Government: And then Pope <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> being informed by ſome Engliſh Jeſuits, that ſuch was the number of Roman Catholicks here, is if he would Excomu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate her, they would preſently enter into an open Hoſtility, with force ſufficient to depoſe and utterly ſupplant her Highneſs, and re-eſtabliſh the Roman faith, whereupon the Pope does Excomuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate her, and Plots with the King of <hi>Spain</hi> to invade her: Then did the Papiſts withdraw themſelves from our Churches: Thus you ſee it was not Conſcience of Duty to Chriſt as it is in the Proteſtant Diſſenters, who own no Authority on Earth but the King and the Laws; but Veneration to the Autority of the Pope the Queens E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies and implaceable hatred of all Proteſtants, that led Papiſts to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110664:8"/>to forſake the Church and their Allegiance, and ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uues them Recuſants; ſo that it is the true intent of the Law, that it ſhould be executed againſt Papiſts; upon this Ground it was, that (as I am well informed) a Grand Jury of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> having Preſentments brought againſt ſeveral great Papiſts, would not find the Bill againſt them for not going to Church till the Conſtable or Witneſſes had given Teſtimony that they were commonly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to be of the Roman Religion, and that the Clerk had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted in the Bill of Indictment, <hi>Pontificiam Religionem Profitentes,</hi> wherein (I judge) they did perſue the true Intent of the Law, in that caſe provided.</p>
            <p>If you ſhall ſtill inſiſt, and ſay, that Papiſts do religiouſly give this Authority to the Pope, I anſwer, Firſt, that that Opinion is ſo manifeſtly contrary to <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> that every man that uſes Reaſon, or owns <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Religion, except Papiſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, muſt condemn it. Think you that a <hi>Mahometan,</hi> or a ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Heathen, upon a fair Hearing of both Parties, would judge the Pope's Pretenſions to his Infallibility and Supremacy reaſonable, or in the leaſt doubt of their Invalidity? But, Secondly, They that would have Liberty of Religion and <hi>Conſcience,</hi> do not pretend to ſuch that is incoſiſtent with the Sovereignty of Independent States and Kingdoms, in things neceſſary to civil Society; much leſs to ſuch a Liberty as ſhall permit Religious Enemies to cut their Throats whenever they can by Watchfulneſs find an Opportunity? Such is that <hi>Conſcience</hi> which this Objection pleads for, as may appear by what I have ſaid above: And the very thing I am pleading a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, is, The depriving Men of their Properties and Liberties up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any Pretence whatſoever, ſaving for a <hi>Crime</hi> that's inconſiſtent with common Liberty and Property: But the <hi>Conſciences</hi> of Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters require nothing but a Liberty to that, which if it were not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, would be ſo far from being hurtful to the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> that it would rather be a Vertue, nothing detracting from, but condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to the <hi>Common Good.</hi> And I hope every honeſt Man will make a difference between thoſe Laws that are neceſſary to the common Cood, and thoſe that are made merely for the Pleaſure of the Law-givers; and which others, as wiſe and <hi>Chriſtian</hi> as they would either null or make contrary. Surely the <hi>Conſciences</hi> exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed about the Obedience of theſe two ſorts of Laws, are far dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent one from another: And that our Penal Laws, ſo far as they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110664:8"/>reſpect Diſſenters, are of ſuch a Nature, as that they are not now to be preſs'd upon Proteſtants who have the Opinion of the Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> in the laſt Parliament at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> Gentlemen of as good <hi>Credit</hi> for Wiſdom, and Love to Proteſtantiſm, and for E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates and Intereſt in their Countries; as perhaps ever was ſeen in <hi>England;</hi> wherein it was reſolved <hi>nemine contradicente, That the Perſecution of the Proteſtant Diſſenters upon the penal Laws, is at this time grievous to the Subject, a weakening to the Proteſtant Intereſt, an Encouragement to Popery, and dangerous to the Peace of the Kingdom.</hi> Jan. 10.</p>
            <p>And now methinks, Sir, you ſhould have as great Reſpect to the Opinion of the whole Nation of Commons in <hi>Parliament,</hi> as you have to the Opinion of his ſingle Grace, my Lord Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> from whom this Order for proſecution of Proteſtant Diſſenters by Preſentments, Excommunications, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> iſſues in flat Contradiction to the Opinion now mentioned, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially conſidering withal the Doubtfulneſs of Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Laws; and all the reſt that I have ſaid and argued in this Caſe, which I preſume may have ſome Influence upon you and any rational honeſt Man. I pray you conſider in the Fear of God, in Honor of Chriſt and his Religion, and in the Love of your Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Neighbours; and do what ſuch Conſideration ſhall direct you to. Take the ſafer Courſe, which is always the more mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in penal Matters. Be ſure you act not againſt Conſcience, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther compell others ſo to do.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your affectionate Friend and Servant.</signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>April</hi> 14. 1683.</date>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
